Now we can talk about some shell commands that are the same for everyone once you're logged on to shell
The zos-unix shell is above all a programmer's interface
The shell has many general tools that can help any programmer and in addition there are several commands designed especially for the C programmer
Shell commands are entered on the command line
Shell command options are usually specified by a minus sign followed by a single character
So for example LS minus L some commands except options that have accompanying arguments
For example LS minus L slash user slash lib the argument may be a number a string a file name or something else a
Shell command can be interrupted and stopped by typing escape character and C
Entering a command with minus question mark or entering it incorrectly results in the command syntax being displayed
Once a shell command begins running it has access to the following three files
standard input with a file descriptor or identifier of zero
standard output file descriptor of one and
standard error with the file descriptor of two a
Shell user can redirect the input output and error files to redirect an output to a file
Enter greater than a file name at the end of a command. For example sort minus you file one greater than out file
If the file does not exist it will be created and if it does exist the output writes over any information in the file
Unless greater than greater than file name is specified to append the output to the existing file
The shell commands are a powerful tool for the shell user because multiple commands can be combined on a single command line
To run a series of commands one after another use a semicolon or use double ampersand and double vertical bar
When stringing multiple commands together these characters can be used to control whether or not the second command should be run
If the command proceeds ampersand ampersand then it completes successfully the second command is run
If the command that proceeds double pipe fails the command following double pipe is run
You can also run more than one command concurrently by using a pipe between the commands
Now the idea of a pipeline is that the output from one command is piped in as input to the next command
Many shell commands are well suited to be used in a pipeline
When a command is entered in the shell another command cannot be entered until the shell prompt appears the job runs as a foreground job
Shell commands that take a long time to complete can be run in the background
The shell does not wait for a job running in the background to complete before presenting a prompt
Because you know it's running in the background
When a shell command is entered a new process is started
The shell runs the command in its own process group
It's considered a separate job and the shell assigns it a job identifier
The job identifier is a number known only to the shell
The system assigns the process a process group identifier or PGID and a process identifier PID
When only one command is entered the PGID is the same as the PID
When multiple commands are entered using a pipe several processes with their own PID will be started
All these processes have the same PGID and shell job number
To check the status of shell commands the commands jobs or PS can be used
The jobs command displays the status of currently running background jobs
And the PS command displays the status of currently running processes
A foreground job can be cancelled by entering a state character plus C
A background job is cancelled by using the kill or super kill command
To stop a foreground job enter escape character and Z
To stop a background job use the kill command for this stop option
And a job can be delayed from running until another background job has completed
by using the wait command
The submit command sends a batch job to the primary job entry subsystem or JES for processing
The file name argument can either be a Unix path name data set or input from the standard input
If the submit command is successful the job ID of the submitted job and the file name are
displayed as part of the output written to standard output unless modified by the minus J option
The JCL must have a job card if a job card is not present
Then the submit command will fail
TSO CMD allows you to run a TSOE command from the shell invoking authorized TSOE commands
Invoke it from a shell script or a prompt
It's best that the TSOE command and its parameters be enclosed in quotes to avoid shell parsing
The COS Unix shell uses environment variables to define characteristics of the shell environment
These variables can be modified to a specific installation or user's needs
Using environment variables provides a flexible method for customizing the shell
The system initiates the shell for the user after the user enters a command to log into the shell
During the initialization the system sets environment variables for the user log name,
home, and shell from information in the rackf user profile
Log name is the user ID that remote systems use when diving into your system
Home is a variable for the path name of the user's working directory
And shell identifies the shell to be invoked
Environment variables can be defined in the rackf user profile, the slash etc slash profile,
the dollar home slash dot profile file, and the file name named in the env environment
variable in a shell command or a shell script
The C shell with all its commands and tools provides a real programmer's interface
It's specifically designed to have a syntax similar to the C programming language
The comparison between the standard and the C shell shows which files are related
and which have to be customized from the system programmer's point of view
Okay, that's a wrap on the COS Unix shell and utilities
You can now escape character in Z out of this process
But before you go, let me share a little bit of good news
The next set of modules I've invited some guest speakers to give you a break from me
So enjoy them!